Realms of Gold: A Catalogue of Maps in the Library of the American Philosophical Society Part I: Manuscript Maps Misc.Maps
American Philosophical Society
- Individually Catalogued Manuscript Maps (Not in Collections)
  - Plan de l'anse à Chouchou dans la partie nord de l'isle de St. Domingue, 1801; 725: 1801: Sa27std: Large; Scale: 1.7 cm. = 50 toises.; Size of paper: 43.5 x 62 cm.; Colored.; Bois St. Lys, Georges Joseph de
    Realms of Gold, 32 (62).
  - Plan de Saint Jean de Puerto Rico, 1801; 728: 1801: Sa27jpr: Large; Scale: 1.7 cm. = 100 toises.; Size: 51.2 x 71.3 cm.; Colored.; Bois St. Lys, Georges Joseph de; López de Vargas Machuca, Tomás, 1731-1802
    Realms of Gold, 32 (63).
  - Plan du mouillage et rade de la Basse Terre dans l'isle de la Tortue, 1801; 725: 1801: Sa27pm: Large; Scale: 2.3 cm. = 50 toises.; Size of paper: 49.5 x 62.1 cm.; Colored.; Bois St. Lys, Georges Joseph de
    Realms of Gold, 32 (64).
  - Special map, representing Man of War Shoal, its distance and bearings from the island of St. Martins, conformable to the discovery of Captain Foulke, Esqr., commanding the British frigate, the Proselite, in the month of May 1801, 733.1: 1800: F143ssm: Small; Size: 20.9 x 27.3 cm.; Fahlberg, Samuel, 1758-1834
    Nicholas Collin delivered this map to the Society on 16 April 1802. Collin wrote that Fahlberg "presentes by me a special map of a lately discovered dangerous shoal...as an appendage to his map of it [St. Bartholomew], sometimes ago received by the Society; and expresses a solicitious desire that it may be published for the benefit of the many American vessels that trade to that part of the West Indies: believeing this execution the more necessary, as the very frigate in which the discovery was made, though then commanded by another captain, ran aground on that shoal." The members desired Secretary John Vaughan to write and see "if any account can be published" of this "Rock lately discovered south of S. Martins."
    Presented by S. Fahlberg, 16 April 1802.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (65).
  - A sketch of the Muscle Shoals of the Tennessee River. Laid down from a Scale of two Computed Miles to the Inch. The Width of the River being doubled, 1802; 663: [1802]: M975sms: Small; Size: 58.6 x 45 cm.; Colored.; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825
    Annotated: "N.B. The red dots mark the Canoe Track by which I descended. The black, note the deepest channel."
    John Vaughan, secretary of the American Philosophical Society, was asked by the Members to get "some further account of it for publication" from the donor. Brown replied on 10 June 1802 that the map "of the Muscle Shoals which you did me the favor to present to the Society, was taken under the direction of Gen[era]l Wilkinson who transmitted it to a friend together with a short description which unluckily was attached to a private confidential letter, from which his correspondent would not even suffer me to make an extract. Gen[era]l Wilkinson will no doubt supply the deficiency on his arrival at Philadelphia."
    Presented by Samuel Brown, April 1802.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (66).
  - [Pennsylvania and neighboring states], 1807; 640.2: [1807]: P376ns: Small; Size: 36 x 50 cm.; Colored.; Pursh, Frederick, 1774-1820
    The endorsement on the back reads: "Found by me in a parcel of Plants collected by F. Pursh w[hi]ch made part of ye Lambert Herbarium, and was bought by me in London at the Lambert sale in 1842. Edward Tuckerman."
    In 1807 Pursh kept a "Journal of a botanical excursion in the Northeastern parts of Pennsylvania and in the state of New York." The manuscript was found among the papers of his patron, Benjamin Smith Barton, in 1817. It has been published twice: first in Philadelphia in 1869, and then in 1923 for the Onondaga Historical Association, Syracuse, New York, with notes by William M. Beauchamp.
    On 3 April 1868 Thomas P. James spoke of various properties of Pursh. He told how the map was drawn and used in the botanical expedition, and he spoke of the history of the map. Asa Gray, the famous botanist, owned it, and wished to present it to the American Philosophical Society and reunite it with the journal. "The Journal and map are now, after a separation of sixty years, united."
    Presented by Asa Gray, 3 April 1868.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (67).
  - Map of the country nine miles west of the city of Philadelphia, and between Darby Creek and Young's ford on the River Schuylkill. Surveyed by order of Gen. Jonathan Williams...of the sub-committee of defence, 28 September 1814; 649.762: 1814: S87dcyf: Large; Scale: 8 inches = 1 mile.; Size: 214 x 180 cm.; Brooke, Robert, 1770-1821; Kneass, William, 1780-1840; Strickland, William, 1787-1854
    Presented by Jonathan Williams, 3 February 1815.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (68).
  - Plan hidrografico de la laguna de Maracaybo, [ca. 1815]; 753: [ca.1815]: M335Lam: Large; Scale: 25 Millas Colombianos de 60 al grado.; Size: 61.6 x 40.6 cm.
    Presented by John Vaughan, 17 July 1815.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (69).
  - Plano del puerto de Guaimas, situado en la costa de Sonora [Mexico]...levantado de orden del gobierno en 1819...p[a]r defensa del puerto y puntos adjacentes à la costa, 1821; 705.3: 1821: N316msg: Small; Scale: Escale de une milla maritima.; Size: 41.9 x 45.2 cm.; Colored.; Negrete, Pedro Celestino, 1777-1846
    The bay contains soundings.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (70).
  - [Plano] de [Orizava] y Xalapa, en la parte que media des la sierra a la costa, 1823; 703.4: 1823: G163xrp: Small; Scale: Escala de neuve legs. del reyno de n.e. de 5000 vars. cadavna.; Size: 35.9 x 53 cm.; Garcias, Diego
    Annotated: "Copiado por Santiago Wilkinson en Mexico."
    Projected route from Vera Cruz with distances to Orizaba, Xalapa, etc.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (71).
  - Chart of the northwest coast of the island of Cuba, between the meridians of Havana and the Cape St. Antonio, 1830; 723: 1830: M365cha: Large; Size: 47.7 x 60.9 cm.; Martinez, Juan J.
    Presented by Juan J. Martinez, 7 December 1832.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (72).
  - Chesapeake and Delaware canal, [ca. 1830]; 651.4: [ca. 1830]: T158cdp: Small; 3 pieces.; Scale: 1.3 cm. = 1,000 yards; 1.9 cm. - 1 mile.; Size: 19.6 x 37.8 cm.; Tanner, Henry Schenck, 1786-1858
    Contains topographical view and vertical section.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (73).
  - Lac Supérieur et autres lieux ou sont les missions des pères de la compagnie de Iesus comprises sous le nom d'Ovtaovacs; Mont Ste. Marie, 1831; 626.2: 1831: Su77cd: Small; Scale: 50 lieues.; Size: 54 x 42.5 cm.
    Annotated: "Facsimile d'une carte attachée à un des volumes des lettres edifiantes pour le Canada dont les Jesuites publierent plus de 40 volumes de 1611 à 1678." ( Relations des Jesuites en la Nouvelle France. Paris: Cramoisy: 1632-1673.)
    A note reads: "rough fac smilie-this and the Scutcheon above are Well drawned and Engraven."
    Realms of Gold, 32 (74).
  - Situate in the counties of Schuylkill and Northampton showing a route for a rail road commencing at the five locks at the Schuylkill canal below Pottsville and ending at the mouth of Lizzard Creek where the same falls into the Lehigh River, being in length 22 miles and 102 perches, intended to constitute a part of the general rail road now in contemplation between Philadelphia and Pottsville, 1831; 649: 1831: D812sur: Large; Size of paper: 46.4 x 187.4 cm.; Colored.; Dreher, John
    Surveyed at the request of William Audenried, Esquire, during the month of June 1831.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (75).
  - [Susquehanna, Schuylkill and little Schuylkill rivers, in Pennsylvania], [ca. 1835]; 649: [ca.1835]: B781msc: Large; Scale: 0.5 inch = 1 mile.; Size of paper: 48.8 x 77.7 cm.; Brobst, Christian
    Annotated: "A copy of a Christian Brobst traycing [and] Cattawissa," and, "W[illia]m J. Duane has the original."
    Realms of Gold, 32 (77).
  - Middle Atlantic states, [ca. 1852]; 640.2: [ca.1852]: At61mas: Small; Scale: 1.5 cm. = 60 miles.; Size: 14.4 x 23.5 cm.; Colored.
    The route of the Pennsylvania Central Railroad is shown from Philadelphia to Pittsburgh.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (78).
  - Charts pertaining to the Second U.S. Grinnell Expedition in search of Sir John Franklin, under the command of Elisha Kent Kane., 1853-1855; 172.3: 1853-55: G895exp: Large; 5.0 Item(s); Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    A member of the American Philosophical Society, Kane spoke on 16 November 1855 of various geographical features of the Arctic regions he had seen and displayed his map of the area. He spoke of the progress of the expedition and the difficulties encountered. On 7 December 1855 he exhibited two charts showing his corrections and the new features described on them. These may be the charts Kane displayed and spoke about. See: American Philosophical Society Proceedings, vol. 7 (1885): pages 154, 162.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (79).
    - [Melville Bay and surrounding area], 1853-1855; Size: 60.4 x 73 cm.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    - [Unidentified], 1853-1855; Size: 44.8 x 63.4 cm.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    - [Base of Sylva Mountain, observatory and brig], 1853-1855; Draft.; Size: 36 x 40.5 cm.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    - Sylva Mountain, position of observatory and brigg, 1853-1855; Size: 18.3 x 20.8 cm.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
      Also includes a printed copy.
  - Wythe County, Virginia. Profile, showing geological strata from Big Walker Mountain to Peak Mountain, [ca. 1854]; 654: [ca.1854]: L565geo: Large; Size: ca. 172.5 x 308 cm.; Colored.; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903
    Realms of Gold, 32 (80).
  - Cumberland and Frobisher Sts. from a drawing by an Eskimo in 1856 given to Capt. Salter of the Clara of Peterhead, 617: 1856: C911cfs: Small; Size of paper: 51 x 43.8 cm.
    See the description of the Boas map in Realms of Gold, No. 6.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (81).
  - Map of the military reservation [on the Columbia River] at Fort Vancouver, W[ashington] T[erritory]. Surveyed under the direction of Capt. Geo. Thom...by Lts. J. B. Wheeler and J. Dixon...By order of Brig. Gen. W. S. Harney, 1859; 697: 1859: Un38fvc: Large; 8.0 Item(s); Photographs.; Scale: 10 inches = 1 mile.; Size: ca. 34 x 25.8 cm.; Dixon, Jeremiah; Harney, William S., (William Selby), 1800-1889; Thom, George; Wheeler, J. B., (Junius Brutus), 1830-1886
    Originals in General Land Office Records, Abandoned Military Reservation Series, Fort Vancouver, Washington. Box 100, National Archives, Washington, D.C.
    Includes photograph of so-called "Covington Map." (Original in Hudson's Bay Company Archives, London, 1846.)
    Includes also photographs from other sources.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (82).
  - Profile showing the comparative levels of the bituminous coal fields and oil district of West Virginia, Ohio, and western Pennsylvania, March 1865; 649: 1865: S37wvop: Large; On linen.; Scales: 5 miles per inch horizontal, and 500 feet per inch vertical.; Size of linen: 31 x 112 cm.; Sheafer, P. W., (Peter Wenrick), b. 1819
    Realms of Gold, 32 (83).
  - Section of the lake, river, and canal navigation from Lake Superior to the Gulf of the St. Lawrence, [ca. 1869]; 670: [ca. 1869]: B561Lsg: Large; Scales: Horizontal: 1 inch = 60 miles; Vertical: 1 inch = 400 feet.; Size: 23 x 85.4 cm.; Colored.; Blackwell, T. E., (Thomas E.)
    With this is a water color painting of "Sketch from the Mountain of Montreal shewing part of the plain extending south east and southwards to the Green Mountain Range in eastern townships of Canada and Vermont and the Adirondack Mountain regions of New York. To illustrate Mr. Blackwell's paper on the basin of the St. Lawrence." See: American Philosophical Society Transactions, Series 2, vol. 13 (1869).
    Realms of Gold, 32 (84).
  - Chart of Niantilic harbor by William A. Mintzer, U.S. Navy, from observations by Lieut. Wilkins, U.S. Navy, navigating officer of the U.S. St. Tigress on Polaris search, 1874; 178: 1874: M667nia: Small; Scale: ½ inch = 1 mile.; Size of paper: 25.9 x 20.6 cm.; Mintzer, William A.; Wilkins, Lieutenant
    Niantilic Harbor is on Baffin Bay, Cumberland Sound. The Polaris had disappeared, and the Tigress and another ship were sent to locate it. The readings for this map are: North lat. 64° 56' - West long. 66° 21'. Also in folder is a map showing "Padloaping. Nettiling Fjord and Nettiling."
    Realms of Gold, 6 (1), 32 (85).
  - [United States coast bordering the Atlantic Ocean and the Gulf of Mexico], [ca. 1885]; 635: [ca.1885]: Un38atL: Large; 8 maps in 13 pieces.; Size: ca. 96 x 60 cm.; Colored.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (86).
  - Geological map of the northern part of the Indian territory, 1896-1897; 667: 1897: D782ind: Large; Scale: 1 inch = 4 miles.; Size: 110 x 89.9 cm.; Drake, N. F., (Noah Fields), b. 1864
    See: N. F. Drake, "A geologial reconnaissance of the coal fields of the Indian territory." American Philosophical Society Proceedings, vol. 36 (1897): pp. 326-419.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (87).
  - [Arctic regions], 1897; 170: 1897: N166arm: Large; Size: 156.5 x 160.3 cm.; Colored.; Nansen, Fridtjof, 1861-1930; Sword, James Brade, 1839-1915
    This is an enlargement made by Sword of a portion of a map. See: Fridtjof Nansen, Farthest North (New York: Harper: 1897), vol. 1.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (88).
  - Philadelphia as William Penn knew it, 1684. Commemoration of the 250th anniversary of the first arrival, October 24, 1682, of William Penn in America, 1682-1932, 649.962: 1932: P766wpp: Small; Scale: 1¾ inches = 600 feet.; Size: 42.5 x 26.6 cm.; Myers, Albert Cook, 1874-1960; Pollard, William Wilson
    Prepared for the program committee [of the 250th anniversary], Albert Cook Myers, chairman.
    Presented by Albert Cook Myers, 28 March 1935.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (89).
  - Plan of ground and site of the residence of Benjamin Franklin. Federal Project "C," Public Law 795, 80th Congress. Approved June 28, 1948. Plate II, 649.962: 1948: G656rbf: Large; Scale: 1 inch = 20 feet.; Size: 39 x 30.7 cm.; Colored.; Gorman, Fred J.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (90).
  - Albemarle sound, North Carolina, 656: n.d.: AL21asm: Small; Size of paper: 38.6 x 48.7 cm.; Colored.
    Roanoke Island is shown, as is Edenton, Hallifax (sic), and the Virginia line.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (91).
  - [Delaware Bay and River], 640.2: n.d.: F533bdr: Small; Size: 41.5 x 23 cm.; Fisher, Joshua Francis, 1807-1873
    This appears to have been adapted directly from the map published in London by Laurie and Whittle in 1794. The identity of the cartographer is an educated guess.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (92).
  - A chart of the world, upon Mercator's projection, with the new discoveries. [Also, the eastern and western hemispheres], 100: n.d.: C382wmd: Small; 3 pieces.; Sizes: 39 x 45.6 cm; and 36 x 36 cm.; Colored.
    These are printed maps with heavy manuscript markings indicating air (?) currents and observations drawn and crudely colored. Antarctica is also drawn on each map.
    The maps were printed in London by "Jas Wyld," and "J. Wyld and Son, Charing Cross East 1836." (One map has no publication date on it.)
    Realms of Gold, 32 (93).
  - [Geological map of part of Switzerland?], 237: n.d.: Swgeo: Small; Size: 12.5 x 18.9 cm.; Colored.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (94).
  - [Central Pennsylvania, showing Danville, Catawissa, and other cities], 649.964: n.d.: C432kpc: Small; In pencil.; Size: 32.9 x 47.6 cm.
    This is on the reverse of C. G. Childs' "Plan of Keim's addition to Port Clinton" (Realms of Gold, 986).
    Realms of Gold, 32 (95).
  - [Sections of Old Philadelphia during the 17th, 18th and 19th centuries], 649.962: n.d.: P376hist: Small; 6.0 Item(s); Size: each sheet ca. 45.2 x 55.5 cm.
    Photostats of manuscript maps at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (96).
  - [Shwemyo district, central Burma. Lat. 20º 3', long. 96º 14'], n.d.; 457: n.d.: B922shw: Small; Size: 47 x 60 cm.; Colored.
    Four lines in Burmese in the lower left-hand corner are the key to the colors used in the map. Note on back in Burmese identifies location as Shwemyo district. See letters from E. W. Burlingame and Cecil Hobbs to the American Philosophical Society, June 1914 and 27 January 1961.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (97).
  - Tabula novae Franciae, 1660. [copy], n.d.; 611: n.d.: C162tnf: Small; Insert: Chorographia regionis Huronum. Hodie desertae.; Size: 34.6 x 44.3 cm.; Colored.; Du Creux, François, 1596?-1666
    Copied from François Du Creux, Historiae Canadensis seu novae Franciae libri decem ad annum usque Christi 1656 (Paris: 1664). This was printed in the Champlain Society Publications, volumes 30-31, translated by Percy J. Robinson (Toronto: 1951).
    A note by P. J. Robinson states that this map deserves study and is of special value on account of the inset map of the Huron country, the improved outline of the lakes, especially Lake Ontario, and Georgian Bay, the marking of the trails to the Hudson Bay and of the new route discovered by the Groseilliers and Radisson from Lake Nipigon.
    Realms of Gold, 32 (98).